A Finding Aid to the Carrig-Rohane Shop Records, 1903-1962, in the Archives of American Art AAA.carrshop
Archives of American Art
Carrig-Rohane Shop records
1903-1962
AAA.carrshop
Archives of American Art
6.7 Linear feet
The Carrig-Rohane Shop records measure 6.7 linear feet and date from 1903 to 1962. The records document the founding of the Boston company, frame design and production, and the financial transactions of the shop. The numerous framing records, such as pattern and specification order books, are particularly valuable for researching and matching custom frames with specific works of art of the late 19th and early 20th century. The frame patterns are also useful for researchers interested in the history of frame design.
Carrig-Rohane Shop
Historical Note
In 1903 Herman Dudley Murphy, Walfred Thulin and Charles Prendergast began making frames and in 1906 H.D. Murphy opened "The Frame Shop of Herman Dudley Murphy" on Clarendon Street in Boston.
According to the meeting minutes, on June 13, 1911, the frame shop incorporated under the name "The Thulin-Murphy Co." with Walfred Thulin as the President. The shop name was then changed to "Carrig-Rohane" on February 5, 1914, and on October 23, 1915, the shop came under the management of Robert Churchill Vose, Sr. and Nathaniel Morton Vose.
The corporation was eventually dissolved on March 29, 1939, and the framing operations moved to the Vose Galleries' premises.
Scope and Content Note
The Carrig-Rohane Shop records date from 1903 to 1962, and measure 6.7 linear feet. The records document the founding of the company, frame design and production, and the financial transactions of the shop. Series 2: Frame Orders and Specifications is particulary valuable for researching the frames used for late 19th and early 20th century American works of art. The frame patterns can be cross-referenced with the orders to obtain visual documentation of the frame desing used with a specific work of art. The frame patterns are also useful for researchers interested in the history of frame design.
The records of the Carrig-Rohane Shop also include financial and business records, printed material, sketches of frames, and photographs of sketches and sculptures.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven series:
Series 1: Frame Patterns, circa 1903-1962 (boxes 1-2, 1 linear ft.)
Series 2: Frame Orders and Specifications, 1904-1962 (boxes 2-5, 3 linear ft.)
Series 3: Financial Records, 1908-1939, undated (boxes 5-7, 1.9 linear ft.)
Series 4: Business Records, 1903-1955, undated (box 7, 11, 0.6 linear ft.)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1906 (box 7, 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 6: Works of Art, 1931, 1936, undated (boxes 7, OV 10, 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 7: Photographs, undated (box 7, 0.1 linear ft.)
Provenance
The Carrig-Rohane Shop records were donated by Robert Churchill Vose, Jr., Duxbury, Massachusetts, April 4, 1974, January 13, 1975, April 5, 1984, February 1, 1986, and March 17, 1987.
Funding for the processing and microfilming of this collection was provided by a grant from the Eli Wilner & Company, Inc., New York, New York.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on microfilm reels 4974-4982. The microfilm is available through interlibrary loan.
Carrig-Rohane Shop (Boston, Mass.); Murphy, Hermann Dudley, 1867-1945; Thulin, Walfred, 1878-1949; Thulin-Murphy (Firm: Boston, Mass.); Vose Galleries of Boston; Vose, Robert Churchill, 1873-; Art, American; Art, Modern -- 20th century -- United States; Photographs; Picture frame industry -- Massachusetts -- Boston; Picture frames and framing; Works of art
- Frame Patterns, circa 1903-1962; Series 1; (boxes 1-2, 0.9 linear ft.)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains photographs of the various frames that were constructed at the shop. Most of the photographs include the pattern number assigned by the Carrig-Rohane Shop for order purposes. There are two groups of numerically ordered frame patterns, one assembled from loose photographs in the collection and the other made from a set of negatives found in the collection. The six bound photograph books, the cyanotype photographs, and the loose photographs of frame patterns are primarily unordered duplicates of the two numerical sets. Included is a price list of frame patterns, as well as a book of frame patterns ordered.
  - Photographs of patterns #1-57, circa 1903-1962 (Box 1, Reel 4974)
  - Photographs of patterns #1-92A and unidentified from slides and negatives, circa 1903-1962 (Box 1, Reel 4974)
  - Negatives and prints of frame patterns, circa 1903-1962 (Box 1)
  - Bound photograph book of frame patterns (original collation), circa 1903-1962 (Box 1, Reel 4974)
  - Photograph album of frame patterns, circa 1903-1962 (Box 1, Reel 4974)
  - Photographs of frame patterns (cyanotypes), circa 1903-1962 (Box 1, Reel 4974)
  - Photographs of frame patterns, circa 1903-1962 (Box 1, Reel 4974)
  - Price list of frame patterns, circa 1903-1962 (Box 2, Reel 4974)
  - Frame patterns ordered, circa 1903-1962 (Box 2, Reel 4974)
- Frame Orders and Specifications, 1904-1962; Series 2; (boxes 2-5, 3.1 linear ft.)
  Information about frame orders and specifications can be found in this series in the order books dated 1904 to 1962. Information includes the patron or gallery who ordered the frame, the artist and often the title of the work of art, the frame pattern number, frame measurements, the color of the frame, and the materials used. The dates for the frame orders extend past the closure of the Carrig-Rohane Shop because frames continued to be made on the premises of Vose Galleries. The Order/Ledger Book contains order numbers 1333-3692 and can be used to cross-reference information about these particular orders which are also found in the general order books. Indexes in several of the Order Books include the order number printed above the page number where the order can be found. Also included are records of frame orders for photographs and mirrors.
  - Orders, 1904-1907 (Box 2, Reel 4974)
  - Orders, 1907-1912 (Box 2, Reel 4974)
  - Orders, 1912-1916 (Box 2, Reel 4974)
  - Orders, 1916-1918 (Box 2, Reel 4974)
  - Orders, 1916-1918 cont. (Box 2, Reel 4975)
  - Orders, 1918-1919 (Box 2, Reel 4975)
  - Orders/Ledger, 1915-1924 (Box 2, Reel 4975)
  - Orders, 1924-1928 (Box 2, Reel 4975)
  - Orders, 1924-1928 cont. (Box 2, Reel 4976)
  - Orders, 1924-1930 (Box 3, Reel 4976)
  - Orders, 1924-1930 cont. (Box 3, Reel 4977)
  - Orders, 1928-1952 (Box 3, Reel 4977)
  - Orders, 1928-1952 cont. (Box 3, Reel 4978)
  - Orders, 1930-1962 (Box 4, Reel 4978)
  - Orders, 1930-1962 cont. (Box 4, Reel 4979)
  - Orders, 1936-1956 (Box 4, Reel 4979)
  - Orders, 1923-1928 (Box 4, Reel 4979)
  - Photograph frames and mirror consignments, 1919-1929 (Box 4, Reel 4979)
  - Frame profiles of orders, 1905-1906 (Box 5, Reel 4979)
  - Mirror orders, 1905-1919 (Box 5, Reel 4979)
- Financial Records, 1908-1939, undated; Series 3; (boxes 5-7, 1.9 linear ft.)
  Financial records are standard and include invoices, accounts receivable ledgers, general ledgers, consignment account ledgers, income tax forms, a cash book, and accounting reports and notes. The reports contain accounts receivable, accounts payable, and trial balances recorded every six months.
  - Invoices, 1923-1930 (Box 5, Reel 4979)
  - Invoices, 1923-1930 cont. (Box 5, Reel 4980)
  - Invoices, 1931-1939 (Box 5, Reel 4980)
  - Accounts receivable, 1915-1923 (Box 5, Reel 4980)
  - Accounts receivable, 1915-1923 cont. (Box 5, Reel 4981)
  - Accounts receivable, 1917-1937 (Box 5, Reel 4981)
  - Accounts receivable, 1917-1937 cont. (Box 6, Reel 4981)
  - General ledger, 1908-1911 (Box 6, Reel 4981)
  - General ledger, 1923-1939 (Box 8, Reel 4981)
  - Consignment accounts ledger, 1915-1916 (Box 6, Reel 4981)
  - Consignment accounts ledger, 1915-1922 (Box 6, Reel 4981)
  - Income tax forms, 1911-1914 (Box 6, Reel 4981)
  - Accounting reports/notes, 1909-1936, undated (Box 6, Reel 4981)
  - Accounting reports/notes, 1909-1936, undated cont. (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Cash book, 1909-1918, undated (Box 9, Reel 4982)
- Business Records, 1903-1955, undated; Series 4; (box 7, 11, 0.6 linear ft.)
  Business records found in this series include scattered official and legal documents for Thulin-Murphy, Inc. and the Carrig-Rohane Shop. Several routine letters can also be found here.
  - Transcribed history notes of R.C. Vose, circa 1903-1939 (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Letters (scattered), 1926, 1927, 1953, 1955, undated (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Thulin-Murphy Incorporation documents, 1911 (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Meeting record book, 1911-1939 (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Stockholder records, 1911-1915, 1922-1933 (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Thulin-Murphy stock certificates, 1911-1922 (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Insurance Policies, 1914 (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Lease extensions, 1906-1913 (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Inventories, 1926, 1927, 1929, 1936-1938 (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Notes, undated (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Ephemera, undated (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Copyright registration, 1905-1909 (Box 11)
  - Letters, 1919-1924 (Box 11)
  - Inventories, 1933-1935 (Box 11)
- Printed material, 1906; Series 5; (box 7, 0.1 linear ft.)
  This series consists of one folder containing a copy of an article, Individual Treatment of the Picture Frame, by Frederick W. Coburn. The article includes discussion of the work of Herman Dudley Murphy, Charles Prendergast and Walfred Thulin.
  - Printed Material, 1906 (Box 7, Reel 4982)
- Works of art, 1931-1936, undated; Series 6; (boxes 7, OV 10, 0.1 linear ft.)
  This series contains detailed sketches of frames drawn in pencil and ink. Most of the sketches have notations such as measurements of the works of art they were intended for, as well as the names of clients purchasing the frame and artists who had produced the artwork to be framed. Some of the sketches are oversized. The series also contains a print and a watercolor sketch by unidentified artists.
  - Sketches of frames, 1931, 1936, undated (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Print and watercolor, undated (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Oversize sketches of frames (Box OV 10, Reel 4982)
- Photographs, undated; Series 7; (box 7, 0.1 linear ft.)
  This series contains 3 folders of photographs. There are several photographs of sketches by famous artists, several photographs of sculpture, primarily of women with children, and a folder of miscellanous photographs showing interiors with frames, furniture, and unidentified individuals.
  - Photographs of Sketches, undated (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Photographs of Sculpture, undated (Box 7, Reel 4982)
  - Photographs, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 7, Reel 4982)